<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
  <channel>
    <title>Charles Barnes</title>
    <description>Charles Barnes - Developer in St. Louis, Mo | charles@charlesabarnes.com</description>
    <link>https://chkb.net/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://chkb.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2025 Charles Barnes</copyright>
    <webMaster>charles@charlesabarnes.com</webMaster>
    <managingEditor>charles@charlesabarnes.com (Charles Barnes)</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:56:46 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:56:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.2</generator>
    <image>
      <url>https://chkb.net/assets/images/blog/default-image.png</url>
      <title>Charles Barnes</title>
      <link>https://chkb.net</link>
    </image>
    
      <item>
        <title>How I Built This Site</title>
        
        <description>I use my personal website as a place to market myself and exhibit my eye for design.  I always spend an inordinate amount of time on it and this time is no different.</description>
        
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="how-i-built-this-site">How I Built This Site</h1>

<p>I use my personal website as a place to market myself and exhibit my eye for design.  I always spend an inordinate amount of time on it and this time is no different. This time I took a much different approach, as I would like to use this site to publicly share things that I used to share on social media.  This comes with a number of requirements for content mangement and hosting.   This blog post is a record of the process I went through to build this site.</p>

<h2 id="requirements">Requirements</h2>

<ul>
  <li>The site must be designed and styled by me.</li>
  <li>The site must be easy to maintain.</li>
  <li>Hosting must be free or very inexpensive.</li>
  <li>Content must be easily indexed by search engines.</li>
  <li>I want to be able to showcase my projects, photography, and various other things I’ve worked on.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="history-of-the-site">History of the site</h2>

<p>Previously hosted at <a href="https://charlesabarnes.com">charlesabarnes.com</a> on bluehost, I used to leave the site as a relatively</p>

<h3 id="2015">~2015</h3>

<p>Only found it indexed at earliest in 2018.  The first version of the site was a simple static site built with HTML and CSS.  It was hosted on bluehost. I made websites before for small businesses and friends and family, but I don’t believe this was my best work. Previous versions of the site was just wordpress sites with no custom design and a theme that I found on the internet.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/2018-charlesabarnes-com.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/2018-charlesabarnes-com.png" alt="2018 version of charlesabarnes.com" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a>
<em><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/2018-charlesabarnes-com.png">View full size</a></em></p>

<h3 id="2020">~2020</h3>

<p>This update to my site was a needed refresh. I decided to give things a go with a new design and a new hosting provider. This was something I wanted to make pretty quickly and flexibly.  I was able to get the site up and running in a few hours.  I used Angular to build the site, but I didn’t use any of the Angular framework, just vanilla javascript.  I used the Angular CLI to generate the project and then I just used the components and services in the project. A lot of the content was driven by json files that I could easily update. The site was hosted on github pages.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/2020-charlesabarnes-com.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/2020-charlesabarnes-com.png" alt="2020 version of charlesabarnes.com" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a>
<em><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/2020-charlesabarnes-com.png">View full size</a></em></p>

<h2 id="design-process">Design Process</h2>

<p>For this revisition I wanted to design the site from the ground up.  Figma made this process much easier than before, so I decided to use it to its fullest extent.</p>

<h3 id="design-concepts">Design Concepts</h3>

<h4 id="iniitial-ideas">Iniitial Ideas</h4>

<p>To start the design process, I was always obsessed with designs that used a lot of tiling icons.  I began by using <a href="https://fontawesome.com/">fontawesome</a> and selecting a number of Icons that I believed best represented my interests.  I then used Figma to lay them out in a grid.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/icon%20selection.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/icon%20selection.png" alt="Icon selection" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a>
<em><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/icon%20selection.png">View full size</a></em></p>

<p>I then thought I wanted the icons to scroll across the screen with a marquee. I decided to do a layout of the site with the marquee and then I would work on the rest of the site.  In this revision I also wanted to highlight <em>why</em> the site is on “chkb.net” and how that title related to me So I decided to highlight the “chkb” in a logo.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-concept.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-concept.png" alt="Home page concept" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a>
<em><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-concept.png">View full size</a></em></p>

<h4 id="blog-posts">Blog Posts</h4>

<p>I liked the color selection and layout.  It felt good to go for a modern neobrutalist look.  I decided it was then time to check out how a list of blog posts would look. with the chosen color scheme.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/blog-concept.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/blog-concept.png" alt="Blog concept" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a>
<em><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/blog-concept.png">View full size</a></em></p>

<p>This was a good start, but it looked amaturish.  I didn’t like the color selection at all.</p>

<h4 id="photography-gallery">Photography Gallery</h4>

<p>I then decided to try out the photography section without colors and borders.  This looked much better.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/gallery-concept.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/gallery-concept.png" alt="Gallery concept" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a>
<em><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/gallery-concept.png">View full size</a></em></p>

<h4 id="grid-concept">Grid Concept</h4>

<p>I decided to go with a grid of icons, just as a way to fill the space. I was hoping to have each icon as a clickable link or a way to open a modal with more information.</p>

<p>I iterated here a few times trying to figure out the best color for this.   I ended up going with the neutral colors that I have now, but I think I will try out some other colors later.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-icon-grid.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-icon-grid.png" alt="Home with colored icons" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a></td>
      <td><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/icon-grid-empty.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/icon-grid-empty.png" alt="Home page with empty icon grid" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-icon-grid-no-color.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-icon-grid-no-color.png" alt="Home with icons (no color)" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a></td>
      <td><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-dark-mode.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-dark-mode.png" alt="Home in dark mode" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h4 id="final-design">Final Design</h4>

<p>In this final design, we have something that looks like the site I am using now.  I didn’t add the informational card to the home page, but I believe it will be something I will add later. I generally dont like the progress bar as a design element, but I have received a lot of positive feedback on it from potential clients and employers.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-info-card.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-info-card.png" alt="Home with info card" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a>
<em><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/home-info-card.png">View full size</a></em></p>

<h2 id="development">Development</h2>

<p>Development on the site was done in 2 stages basically. The first stage was to get something up and running quickly.  The second stage was to add the features and styling that I wanted.</p>

<h3 id="first-stage">First Stage</h3>

<p>wanted to get the site up and running because I was tired of the old site and wanted to get something new up.  I also wanted to get the domain chkb.net to use. I was surprised I was able to get such a short domain easily.</p>

<p>This version started off as basic HTML and CSS.  I wanted to get keep the site as simple as possible, hand crafting the site as much as possible.</p>

<h3 id="second-stage">Second Stage</h3>

<p>After almost a year of not working on the site, and after a recent start to a job search, I decided to finish out the site that I initially thought up.</p>

<p>I had some frustrations with the basic HTML and CSS, as I needed to repeat myself a lot.  So I decided to choose some sort of templating system.  I chose Jekyll, as it is a static site generator that is very popular and easy to use. It uses liquid for templating and has a lot of built in features that make it easy to manage the site.</p>

<h4 id="current-site">Current Site</h4>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center"><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/current-home.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/current-home.png" alt="Current home page" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a></th>
      <th style="text-align: center"><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/current-blog.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/current-blog.png" alt="Current blog page" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong>Home Page</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong>Blog Page</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center"><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/current-gallery.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/current-gallery.png" alt="Current gallery page" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a></th>
      <th style="text-align: center"><a href="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/current-portfolio.png"><img src="/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/current-portfolio.png" alt="Current portfolio page" style="width:40vw;max-width:600px;" /></a></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong>Gallery Page</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><strong>Portfolio Page</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>This is the current state of the site. I am still working on it and will be adding more features and styling as I go, but I am happy with the progress so far. I have met all of the requirements that I set out to do.</p>

<h2 id="future-plans">Future Plans</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Add a search bar to the site.</li>
  <li>Keep adding more content to the site.</li>
  <li>Utilize the github api to pull in projects and display them on the site.</li>
  <li>Add dark mode.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://chkb.net/coding/jekyll/github%20pages/2025/03/18/how-i-built-this-site.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://chkb.net/coding/jekyll/github%20pages/2025/03/18/how-i-built-this-site.html</guid>
        <author>charles@charlesabarnes.com (Charles Barnes)</author>
        
        <media:content url="https://chkb.net/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/blog-cover.png" medium="image" />
        <media:thumbnail url="https://chkb.net/assets/images/blog/2025-03-18-personal-site/blog-cover.png" />
        
        
        <category>coding</category>
        
        <category>css</category>
        
        <category>html</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>